Register to The Lowell Mason Papers
Yale University Music Library
The Lowell Mason Papers
1813-1980
MSS 33
Yale University Music Library
9
(15 boxes)
Music, correspondence and other papers, photographs, and additional materials by and about the American composer and educator Lowell Mason (1792-1872)
Mason, Lowell, 1792-1872
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open to researchers by appointment. There are no restricted materials in the collection. Please contact the Special Collections staff to schedule an appointment.
Some of the materials may be stored at the Library's off-campus shelving facility, so researchers should allow at least two business days to have the appropriate boxes paged.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Lowell Mason Papers were given to Yale University by the Mason family in 1873.
Arrangement
In 9 series as follows: I. Music. II. Correspondence. III. Programs. IV. Clippings. V. Writings. VI. Biographical Information. VII. Memorabilia. VIII. William Mason. IX. Old Catalog Cards and Librarian's Notes Concerning the Lowell Mason Collection.
Scope and Contents
The Lowell Mason Papers contain holograph, manuscript, and printed music by Lowell Mason and others, correspondence, programs, clippings, writings, biographical information, and memorabilia, mostly from the period between 1830 and 1870. There are well over 200 hymn-tunes, songs, rounds, and sketches composed or arranged by Mason, many of them in his hand. The journals from Mason's two trans-Atlantic trips elucidate his relationship with his European contemporaries in education and composition. The largest series in the Papers is correspondence. There are about 350 letters, approximately 145 of them by Mason. These include correspondence with such people as Horace Mann, Hans Georg Nägeli, Sigismund Neukomm, and William Channing Woodbridge.
The Lowell Mason Papers include some items from the Mason family's initial gift of the Lowell Mason Library in 1873. These consist of some printed and manuscript music by Lowell Mason and others, programs, and writings by Lowell Mason.
The remainder of the Papers came from several sources. On 17 March 1968 Mrs. William Endicott (née Helen Mason, daughter of Henry Lowell Mason) gave Yale the three-volume typescript of her father's biography and sixteen letters from Horace Mann to Lowell Mason dating from 1844 to 1855. In 1972 Mrs. Elizabeth Mason Ginnel (Henry's niece, daughter of Edward Palmer Mason) gave Yale the portrait of Lowell Mason that now hangs in the Librarian's office, and in 1975 she donated a photograph of Mason's birthplace. Five letters were purchased from Goodspeed's Book Shop in 1970, and one was purchased from Midland Rare Book Company in 1961. Finally, the biographical information in series VI consists mostly of items transferred from the Music Library's general collection.
A series in the Papers is provided for the papers of Lowell Mason's son, William Mason (1829-1908). This series includes published piano music composed or arranged by William Mason, correspondence (1898-1936), clippings, and miscellaneous items. The source of these items is undetermined.
Much of the correspondence, two of Mason's diaries, journals from his European trips, clippings, photographs, and the holograph music by Mason, are a gift from the estate of his grandson, Henry Lowell Mason, in 1970. He used these items as material for a biography of his grandfather, which he worked on from 1909 until his death in 1957. A sub-series in the correspondence is apportioned to Henry Lowell Mason's correspondence concerning his biography.
Additional Lowell Mason correspondence acquired after 1982 has been cataloged separately in the Gilmore Music Library's Miscellaneous Letters Collection.
It is important to distinguish the Lowell Mason Papers from the larger assemblage known as the Lowell Mason Library or Collection. The Mason Library consists of a gift of approximately 10,300 items from the Mason family to Yale in 1873, the year after Mason's death. Its treasures became the core of the impressive rare book collection in the Gilmore Music Library today. The Mason Library includes manuscript and printed music, theoretical treatises, hymnals and other sacred music, hymnological studies, school songbooks, periodicals, and pamphlets. The dates of these items range from the late sixteenth century to 1870, with the bulk of them originating between 1750 and 1850. Between 1874 and 1877, Joel Sumner Smith produced a handwritten catalog and shelf list of the Mason Library. These may be consulted at the Gilmore Music Library, or purchased on microfilm. Many items from the Mason Library also appear in either Orbis (Yale's online catalog) or the Music Library's manuscript card catalog.
The Mason Library was initially deposited in the Yale Divinity Library. After the establishment of the Music Library, most of it was transferred, but certain items remain in the Divinity Library, notably hymnals that contain text but not music.
Biographical / Historical
Lowell Mason, who has been called as "the father of American Church music," was born in Medfield, Massachusetts on 8 January 1792. He came from a musical family, and as a boy he played a wide variety of instruments and attended singing schools. By the age of 16, he was directing his own church choir.
From 1813 to 1827, he lived in Savannah, Georgia, where worked as a businessman and church musician, and studied music with Frederick Abel. In 1822 Mason published a compilation of hymns from a variety of sources under the title The Boston Handel and Haydn Society Collection of Church Music. It proved to be a resounding success, and went through some 22 editions. In the ensuing decades, Mason would publish a vast amount of music, the majority of it intended for practical use in churches and schools. In addition to his work as an editor and arranger, Mason composed many hymns of his own, including "Nearer, My God to Thee," "My Faith Looks Up to Thee," and "From Greenland's Icy Mountains."
In 1827 Mason moved to Boston, where he held a series of increasingly prominent positions as a church musician, and became president of the Boston Handel and Haydn Society. He also developed an extraordinary reputation as a music educator. Beginning as a Sunday school teacher, Mason taught in private schools, established the Boston Academy of Music, organized teacher training conventions, and published numerous pedagogical works. A pioneering advocate for the place of music in public education, he served as superintendent of music in the Boston school system from 1837 to 1851.
In 1837 and again in 1851-1853, Mason traveled to Europe, where he met musicians and educators, delivered lectures, and purchased large numbers of books, scores, and manuscripts, including the library of the German organist J.C.H. Rinck.
In 1854 Mason settled in Orange, New Jersey, where he died on August 11, 1872. The Mason name remained a prominent part of the American musical scene, however, thanks to his sons Daniel Gregory and Lowell (both music publishers), his son William (a pianist), his son Henry (founder of the Mason & Hamlin piano manufacturing company), and his grandson Daniel Gregory (a composer and professor at Columbia University).
Composers -- Correspondence; Composers -- Diaries; Hymns; Music -- United States -- 19th century; Music -- United States -- 20th Century; Piano music; Songs; Appel, Richard G. (Richard Gilmore); Bacon, George B. (George Blagden), 1836-1876; Curwen, John, 1816-1880; Damrosch, Frank, 1859-1937; Dickinson, Edward, 1853-1946; Earhart, Will; Erk, Ludwig, 1807-1883; Foster, Frank Hugh, 1851-1935; Hood, George; Kirk, Edward Norris, 1802-1874; Krohn, Ernst C. (Ernst Christopher), 1888-1975; Lord, Melvin, 1791-1876; Lyon, Mary, 1797-1849; Mann, Horace, 1796-1859; Mason, Abigail Gregory, 1797-1889; Mason, Daniel Gregory, 1873-1953; Mason, Henry Lowell, 1864-1957; Mason, Lowell, 1792-1872; Mason, William, 1829-1908; Milligan, Harold Vincent, 1888-1951; Morgan, J. Pierpont (John Pierpont), 1837-1913; Nägeli, Hans Georg, 1773-1836; Neukomm, Sigismund, Ritter von, 1778-1858; Palmer, Charles Ray, 1834-1914; Park, Edwards Amasa, 1808-1900; Root, Frederic W. (Frederic Woodman), 1846-1916; Smith, Carleton Sprague, 1905-1994; Thayer, Alexander Wheelock, 1817-1897; Tourjée, Eben, 1834-1891; Webb, George James, 1803-1887; Whittemore, Thomas, 1800-1861
- Music, Series I
  - Manuscript Hymn-tunes, Songs, Sketches, etc., I.A
    General
    Probably all by or arranged by Lowell Mason and in his hand.
    - Manuscript Hymn-tunes, Songs, Sketches, etc., 143 items. (Box 1, Folder 1-21)
      Arranged alphabetically by first line, miscellaneous unidentified items at the end.
    - "...Collection of Ps. & HY. Tunes copied & harmonized by Lowell Mason - Savannah, Geo. 1819 & 1820 - published with some alterations as the Boston Handel and Haydn Society Collection of Church Music in 1821.", 1 item; [174] p.; 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Holograph in ink.
    - Sketchbook, 1 item; [22] p.; 24 x 30 cm. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Manuscript Rounds (Including Sketches), I.B
    - Labeled "rounds" by Henry Lowell Mason, 49 items. (Box 2, Folder 1-8)
      Arranged alphabetically by title, miscellaneous unidentified items at the end.
  - Manuscript Music by Others, I.C
    Probably arranged by Lowell Mason and mainly in his hand.
    Arranged alphabetically by composer.
    - Manuscript Music, 25 items. (Box 2, Folder 9-20)
      Includes works or arrangements of works by Beethoven, Nägeli, and Rinck as well as others.
  - Manuscript Hymn and Song Texts, I.D
    Probably translated by Lowell Mason and many in his hand.
    - Manuscript Hymn and Song Texts, 190 items. (Box 2, Folder 21-32)
      Includes texts arranged alphabetically and labeled: Erk?, Falk, Fink, Gersbach, Hauptman, Hayden, Hermann, Keller, Kocher, Kreutzer, Liederkrantz, Kindner, Löwe, Mason, Nägeli, Pax?, Popper?, Reissiger, Richter, Silcher, Schugt, Wachsmann, Wordsworth, and miscellaneous unidentified texts at the end.
      Mostly manuscripts.
  - Printed Music by or Arranged by Lowell Mason, I.E
    Arranged alphabetically by title.
    - [Aulis] Aulis: S.M. For a Double Choir. - S.l.: s.n., no date, 2 items; 1 score (2 p.); 18 x 27 cm. (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Two copies.
    - [Bright source of everlasting love] Bright source of everlasting love: [Hymn]. - [Boston: A.J. Wright, Printer], no date, 3 items; 1 score (6 p.) 16 x 25 cm. (Box 3, Folder 2)
      For chorus.
      "Church Psalmody, Hy. 660" - caption title.
      Three copies.
    - [Christ hath arisen] Christ hath arisen: a carol for Easter. - New York: Mason Brothers, 1863., 1 item; 1 close score ([2] p.); 22 cm. (Box 3, Folder 3)
      For chorus?
      Words by Rev. E.A. Washburn.
    - [Christmas carol] Christmas carol / words by Marie Mason. - S.l.: s.n., no date, 1 item; 1 score ([1] sheet); 30 cm. (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Attributed to Lowell Mason.
    - [Columbia's birth-day, again we behold] Columbia's birth-day, again we behold: ode for 4th July, 1836 / words by H.F. Gould... - [Boston]: Shepley & Wright, Printers, [1886]., 1 item; 1 score (6 p.); 17 x 28 cm. (Box 3, Folder 5)
      For chorus (SATB), unacc.
      With: Stegman's "We hail the day" (pp. 9-12); and an arr. of Handel's "May God on whom all nations wait" (pp. 13-16).
    - [Come, brothers, let us onward] Come, brothers, let us onward: [Pilgrim song]. - S.l.: s.n., no date, 1 item; 1 score ([1] sheet); 19 x 27 cm. (Box 3, Folder 6)
      One sheet from a hymn book?
      With: "Press forward."
    - [Duty's call] Duty's call: "Softly close the shades of Twilight"; parting song of class of 1868, State Normal School, Westfield, Mass." - S.l.: s.n., no date, 1 item; 1 score ([2] sheets); 18 x 25 cm. (Box 3, Folder 7)
      For chorus (SAT).
      Words by Sadie E. Oven.
    - [Elegy of David] Elegy of David: on the death of Saul, and Jonathan. - S.l.: s.n., no date, 1 item; 1 close score (pp. 4-5); 22 cm. (Box 3, Folder 20)
      With: "Psalm 100"; "Song of Moses at the Red Sea"; and "35th psalm."
    - [Gloria in excelsis] Gloria in excelsis: as sung by the choir of the Central Church, Boston / composed, and most respectfully dedicated to the Rev. Wm. M. Rogers by Lowell Mason. - [Boston]: A.J. Wright, Printer, 1844., 1 item; 1 close score (4 p.); 26 cm. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - [He that dwelleth...] S.l.: s.n., no date, 1 item; 1 close score ([1] p.); 18 x 27 cm. (Box 3, Folder 12)
      With: "I love the Lord."
    - [How beautiful, & c.] S.l.: s.n., no date, 1 item; 1 score ([2] p.); 28 cm. (Box 3, Folder 9)
      With "Hymn x. 1st Book."
    - [Hymn for the fatherless and widow society] S.l.; s.n., [1832], 1 item; 1 score (8 p.); 16 x 26 cm. (Box 3, Folder 10)
      Words by S.F. Smith.
      "October, 1832" - caption title.
    - [Hymn 454] S.l.: s.n., no date, 1 item; 1 score (3 p.); 18 x 28 cm. (Box 3, Folder 11)
      With: "Psalm 150-2." (p. 4).
    - [I love the Lord] S.l.: s.n., no date, 1 item; 1 close score ([1] p.); 18 x 28 cm. (Box 3, Folder 12)
      "Selection 16. Quadruple chant" - caption title.
      "Psalm 116 (King James)" - added in pencil.
      With: "He that dwelleth..." (p. [2]).
    - [I was glad when they said unto me] I was glad when they said unto me: anthem for the re-opening of the Bowdoin Street Church, August 21, 1842. - [Boston]: Kidder and Wright, Printers, [1842?]., 1 item; 1 score (8 p.); 16 x 26 cm. (Box 3, Folder 13)
      For SATB, unacc.
      "Psalm 122" - caption title.
    - [I will extol thee, my God, O king] I will extol thee, my God, O king: anthem. - Boston: Kidder & Wright Printers; For sale by C.J. Hendee, 1836., 1 item; 1 score (8 p.); 17 x 26 cm. (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - [The little pilgrims] S.l.: s.n., no date, 1 item; 1 close score ([1] sheet); 18 x 27 cm. (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - [Ode] S.l.: s.n., [1835], 1 item; 1 score (pp. 7-11, [1]); 16 x 26 cm. (Box 3, Folder 16)
      Words by Grenville Mellen on last page, preceded by the words to "Ode" by Park Benjamin.
    - [On thy church, O Power Divine] On thy church, O Power Divine: Church Psalmody, Ps. 67, 5th Pt. - S.l.: s.n., no date, 1 item; 1 score (2 p.); 15 x 26 cm. (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - [135th Psalm] 135th Psalm: composed at the Dedication of the Temple, and always sung in the Temple service. - S.l.: s.n., no date, 1 item; 1 score (pp. 6-7); 22 cm. (Box 3, Folder 17)
      With: "Psalm 100"; "Song of Moses at the Red Sea"; and "Elegy of David."
    - [Our labor here is done] Our labor here is done: State Normal School, Westfield, Mass. Parting song for the class of February, 1869. - S.l.: s.n., [1869?], 1 item; 1 score ([1] sheet) 17 x 25 cm. (Box 3, Folder 18)
      For chorus, unacc.
      Words by Lotta L. Noyes.
    - [Three patriotic songs] Three patriotic songs: suitable for the public celebration of American independence, on the 4th of July. - Boston: Tappan & Dennet, 1842., 1 item; 3 close scores ([3] p.); 16 x 26 cm. (Box 3, Folder 19)
      Contents: For thee, my native land, for thee - For freedom, honor and native land - God bless our native land.
    - [Press forward] S.l.: s.n., no date, 1 item; 1 score ([1] sheet); 19 x 27 cm. (Box 3, Folder 6)
      With: "Come, brothers, let us onward."
    - [Psalm 100] Psalm 100: composed by David for opening of Divine Worship. - S.l. s.n., no date, 1 item; 1 chorus score (p.1); 22 cm. (Box 3, Folder 20)
      With: "Song of Moses at the Red Sea" (pp. 2-3); "Elegy of David" (pp. 4-5); and "135th Psalm" (pp. 6-7).
    - [Sentence] Sentence / written for the Light Street Choir Baltimore, at the request of C. Tiffany, by his friend L. Mason. - S.l.: s.n., no date, 1 item; 1 score (3 p.); 16 x 26 cm. (Box 3, Folder 21)
      With: J. Fawcett's "Wrestling" (p. 4).
    - [Songs prepared for the city celebration of fourth of July, 1845] Boston: A.B. Kidder, 1845., 1 item; 3 close scores (4p.); 17 x 30 cm. (Box 3, Folder 22)
      Contents: "Ode. Thrice hail, happy day"; "Ode. When stern oppression's iron rod"; and "Hymn. God bless our native land."
    - [State Normal School, Westfield, Mass. Song of farewell for the graduating class, February, 1870] S.l.: s.n., [1870?], 1 item; 1 close score ([1] sheet); 25 cm. (Box 3, Folder 23)
      Words by Harriet E. Leonard.
    - [Thanksgiving anthem] Boston: Printed by Kidder, Wright; For sale by Jenks & Palmer, 1840., 1 item; 1 score (8 p.); 16 x 26 cm. (Box 3, Folder 24)
      Words selected from the 147th Psalm, verses 12-20.
    - [Two sanctuses and anthem] Two sanctuses and anthem: revised and re-arranged; from Congregational Church music, Part II - London: Ward & Co., no date, 2 items; 3 scores (3 p.); 15 x 17 cm. (Box 3, Folder 25)
      Includes an earlier edition published by J. Unwin which includes revisions in pencil (by Lowell Mason?).
    - [Watchman tell us of the night] Watchman tell us of the night: a missionary or Christian hymn. - Boston: C. Bradlee, 1830 Jan 28., 1 item; 1 score (2 p.); 24 cm. (Box 3, Folder 26)
      For solo voices (3), chorus, and piano.
      Words by Bowring.
      "Sung at the monthly concert, Park St. Church, Boston" - caption title.
    - [Wedding hymn] [Boston: A. Wright, Printer], no date, 1 item; 1 score (4 p.); 19 x 26 cm. (Box 3, Folder 27)
      For solo voice and chorus (SATB), unacc.
      Words by Ray Palmer.
    - Miscellaneous hymns and anthems by or arranged by Lowell Mason: S.l.: s.n., no date, 1 item; pp. 18-33; 15 x 18 cm. (Box 3, Folder 28)
      Includes: "Watts," "Hebron," "Hamburg," "Holborn," "Etley," "Grays," and "Holiness becometh Thine house."
  - Excerpts or Incomplete Works of Others Belonging to Lowell Mason, I.F
    Arranged alphabetically by composer or title, miscellaneous unidentified works at the end.
    - Excerpts or Incomplete Works of Others Belonging to Lowell Mason, Bartholomew, Ann Sheppard (Mounsey)
      See: Mounsey, Ann Sheppard.
    - O love the Lord. - S.l.: s.n., no date, Goldwin, J.; 1 item; 1 score (4 p.); 27 cm. (Box 3, Folder 29)
      For chorus (SATB) and organ or piano.
    - [Wöchentliche Nachrichten?] - S.l.: s.n., [1767 Jan 27?], 1 item; pp. 239-242; 24 cm. (Box 3, Folder 30)
      Creator unknown, possibly Johann Adam Hiller.
    - [Journal de chant & musique d'église?] [Journal de chant & musique d'église / rédigé par Mr. Nicou-Choron. - Paris Nicou-Choron et Cannaux?], 1837., 1 item; p. 17-20; 18 x 27 cm. (Box 3, Folder 31)
      Incomplete, only includes Salieri's "Salve Regina."
      "Lowell Mason, Paris, July 8th, 1852" - in pencil on p. 17.
    - [Choral music] - S.l.: s.n., no date, Mounsey, Ann Sheppard; 1 item; [8] p.; 12 x 18 cm. (Box 3, Folder 32)
      Portion of a larger work?
      Contents: Man's Medley / words by George Herbert - The cuckoo / words by W. Bartholomew - Sweet day / words by George Herbert - We sing the scale.
    - Fall of Jerusalem., 2 items. (Box 3, Folder 33)
      Manuscript in ink.
      Words by Milman?
      Second tenor and first bass parts only.
      Parts include 3 sheets (2 p. each) from a printed edition. Creator unknown, possibly George Frederick Perry
    - Doxology. - S.l.: s.n., no date, 1 item; [2] p.; 22 cm. (Box 3, Folder 34)
      Creator unknown, possibly Andreas Jakob Romberg.
    - Ode. - S.l.: s.n., no date, Webb, George James; 1 item; 1 score (6 p.); 16 x 25 cm. (Box 3, Folder 35)
      Words by Park Benjamin.
    - Miscellaneous unidentified pieces., 10 items. (Box 3, Folder 36)
      Manuscript and printed.
- Correspondence, Series II
  All correspondence is arranged alphabetically by sender or recipient.
  The correspondence includes a number of transcriptions. The phrase "typescript transcriptions" may refer to some or all of the items in an entry.
  Some cross-references exist from individual members to corporate entries.
  Recent library correspondence is housed in the reference file in the office.
  - Lowell Mason and Relatives, II.A
    Including correspondence from Lowell Mason unless otherwise stated.
    - Cary, Harriet Newell (Mrs. Christopher C.), 1863-1866; 3 items. (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Typescript transcriptions.
    - Gregory, Hannah [mother-in-law], 1851-1860; 2 items. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Mason, Abigail Gregory [wife], 1864-1870; 2 items. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Mason, Alan Gregory [grandson], 1871 Dec 1; 3 items. (Box 4, Folder 4)
      Includes a note by Alan.
    - Mason, Daniel Gregory and wife [son], 1858-1866; 12 items. (Box 4, Folder 5)
      Includes autograph letter signed to sons Daniel and Lowell, and faded copy of Daniel's obituary.
    - Mason, John B. [grandson], 1865 Nov 12; 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Mason, Johnson and family [father and mother], 1814 Jun 8; 2 items. (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Mason, Johnson [father], 1856 Jan 8; 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 8)
      To Lowell Mason.
    - Mason, Johnson and Sally [brother], 1813-1866; 4 items. (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Mason, Lowell, 3rd ("Lolo") [grandson], 1852-1865; 64 items. (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
  - Abigail Gregory Mason, II.B
    From Abigail Gregory Mason to others unless otherwise stated.
    - Bacon, Leonard, Rev., 1878 Mar 23; 2 items. (Box 4, Folder 12)
      Includes notes by Henry Lowell Mason.
    - Cary, Harriet [niece], 1866-89; 3 items. (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Dana, M.E., 1870 Aug 31; 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 14)
      To Abigail.
    - Gregory, Hannah, 1822-1852; 2 items. (Box 4, Folder 15)
      Includes autograph letter signed to Abigail.
    - Mason, Henry ("Harry"), 1881-1884; 3 items. (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Mason, Lowell, 2nd [son], 1839 Jun 22; 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Mason, Lowell, 3rd, 1850; 2 items. (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Mason, Mary Wilhelmina [granddaughter], 1889 Apr 15; 2 items. (Box 4, Folder 19)
      Includes letter from Lowell Mason to Uncle Harry.
    - Reid, Julia M., 1852 Aug 5; 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Russell, Nellie (Mrs. Thomas), no date; 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 21)
      Envelope only.
    - Stone, Martha, 1868 Feb 5; 3 items. (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Mason and Gregory Relatives to One Another, II.C
    - Mason, Abigail Hall, 1867 Nov 11; 2 items. (Box 4, Folder 23)
      To Harriet Mason Carey.
    - Mason, Daniel, 1936 Apr 2; 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 24)
      To Harry Mason.
    - Mason, Henry, 1888 May 8; 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 25)
      To Martha B. Heard.
    - Mason, Henry, 1936 Mar 25; 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 25)
      To Daniel Mason.
    - Mason, Henry, 1852 Sep 2; 2 items. (Box 4, Folder 25)
      To William Mason.
      Envelope enclosed.
    - Mason, Lowell, 2nd, 1851 Feb 2; 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 26)
      To Hannah Buckminster Gregory.
    - Mason, Lowell, 2nd, 1884 Dec 22; 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 26)
      To Henry Lowell Mason.
    - Mason, Sara Smith, 1817 Jan 8; 2 items. (Box 4, Folder 27)
      To Catherine J. Mason and Lucretia Tucker.
    - Mason, William, 1883 Dec 9; 2 items. (Box 4, Folder 28)
      To Helen "Nellie" Palmer Mason.
      Program enclosed.
    - Mason, William, 1890 Apr 17; 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Topics and General, II.D
    - Anderson, George W., 1827 Jun 12; 3 items. (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Bacon, Rev. George Blagden (Box 4, Folder 30)
      List of Bacon correspondence by Henry Lowell Mason.
      - Bacon, Frances J. Mills (Mrs. George Blagden Bacon) to her father or father in-law, 1876 Nov 14; 1 item.
      - Mason, Lowell, to Bacon., 1860-1872; 8 items.
      - Mason, Lowell, 2nd, to Bacon and his wife, 1861-1876; 2 items.
      - Mason, Marie (Mrs. Lowell Mason, 2nd), 1862-1865; 5 items.
        Includes 4 poems and a note to George Blagden Bacon and his daughter, Katherine.
    - Banister, Mrs., 1846 Apr 7; 2 items. (Box 4, Folder 31)
      Includes note re provenance by Henry Lowell Mason
    - Bartlett, Mr., no year Jul 19; 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Bates, R.E.
      See: Boston. Central Congregational Society
    - Beck, Lydia A., 1909-1914; 5 items. (Box 4, Folder 33)